<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic class="popup" template="Popup" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../helpproject.xsd">
  <title translate="true">View Composer Property Inspector_Summary</title>
  <body>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">The </text><text styleclass="Program Feature" translate="true">Property Inspector Pane </text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">is used to view and modify the properties (published aspects) of the currently selected view.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Notes"><text styleclass="Notes" translate="true">Note that, in prior versions of Dolphin, this was known as the </text><text styleclass="Notes" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">Published Aspect Inspector</text><text styleclass="Notes" translate="true">. We&apos;ve taken to calling it to the </text><text styleclass="Notes" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">Property Inspector</text><text styleclass="Notes" translate="true"> in this version because we felt this would be a name which was more familiar to users of other GUI development tools. Take it as read that, in this situation, &#160;Properties and Published Aspects are synonymous.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal Head"><text styleclass="Normal Head" translate="true">Common Operations</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">The top area of this pane shows the available properties of the selected view along with a short textual representation of their values. As you select a property in this tree, one or more editors for the value are displayed in the tabs at the bottom of the pane. </text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">You will find that there will always be a workspace (ST) tab here that can be used to enter a Smalltalk expression to evaluate and assign as the value of the property (using </text><text styleclass="Menu Command" translate="true">Accept</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> from the context menu). Depending on the type of the property being edited there may also be other tabs available with more appropriate editing facilities. For example, if you select a boolean property like </text><text styleclass="Class Name" translate="true">#hasCaption</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> then an additional check box tab will be available to provide a &#160;more straightforward graphical way of editing this value.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">When it is not possible to display a more appropriate editor in situ, but one is available as a dialog, then double-clicking on the property name will bring up this dialog for you. For example, if you double-click on </text><text styleclass="Class Name" translate="true">#backcolor</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> you will launch a standard Windows colour picker that can be used to assign a chosen colour to the property.</text></para>
  </body>
</topic>
