<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title translate="true">Breaking into code loops</title>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1"><text styleclass="Heading1" translate="true">Breaking into code loops</text></para>
    </header>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Dolphin Smalltalk runs a multiprocessing environment where one of the processes is dedicated to receiving user input. Most of the time, when you evaluate code in a </text><text styleclass="Program Feature" translate="true">Workspace,</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> this will be executed on the user input thread. You can see this because, if you perform a time-consuming operation, the user interface will pause until it has completed. </text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Unfortunately, there&apos;s always the possibility that you may cause something to happen on the user interface process which either never terminates or at least takes a very long time to complete. This may be due to a programming error in the underlying code that you are executing or just a mistake in the code you are evaluating. The end result will be that Dolphin will appear to &quot;lock up&quot; and control will not return to the user interface.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Notes"><text styleclass="Notes" translate="true">In fact, in these circumstances, Dolphin hasn&apos;t &quot;locked up&quot; it is just executing in a very tight loop inside the virtual machine.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Fortunately, there is usually a way to break into such a loop and you can do this by typing </text><text styleclass="Menu Command" translate="true">Ctrl+Break</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">. You may have to type this key combination several times because, in order to avoid wasting unnecessary processor cycles, the VM doesn&apos;t look for this break sequence very often. Once the </text><text styleclass="Menu Command" translate="true">Ctrl+Break</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> has been registered a walkback will appear and you can enter the </text><text styleclass="Program Feature" translate="true">Debugger</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> to find out what was causing the infinite cycle.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Notes"><text styleclass="Notes" translate="true">Note, it may not always be possible to break into a code loop. If the loop is performing very low level bytecode operations such as large integer arithmetic calculations, the virtual machine may not be checking for the </text><text styleclass="Notes" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Ctrl+Break</text><text styleclass="Notes" translate="true"> key press. If this is the case and you have typed </text><text styleclass="Notes" style="font-style:italic;" translate="true">Ctrl+Break</text><text styleclass="Notes" translate="true"> several times without success, there may be nothing for it but to terminate Dolphin using the </text><text styleclass="Notes" style="font-weight:bold;" translate="true">Windows Task &#160;Manager</text><text styleclass="Notes" translate="true">. </text></para>
  </body>
</topic>
