<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title translate="true">The Socket Connection Interface</title>
  <keywords>
    <keyword translate="true">The Socket Connection Interface</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1"><text styleclass="Heading1" translate="true">The Socket Connection Interface</text></para>
    </header>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">The Dolphin </text><text styleclass="Program Feature" translate="true">Sockets Connection </text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">package provides several levels of interface to the underlying Windows Sockets layer.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">The lowest level of interface is provided by the </text><text styleclass="Class Name" translate="true">WSockLibrary</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> class, which is an </text><text styleclass="Class Name" translate="true">ExternalLibrary</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> subclass responsible for interface into the function calls in the Windows Sockets, </text><text styleclass="Class Name" translate="true">WSOCK32.DLL</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> library. We provide methods for most of the functions in this library. Most often, you will find that the higher levels of interface provided by </text><text styleclass="Program Feature" translate="true">Sockets Connection</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> will be more than adequate for your networking needs but, if you find that you need to add facilities, you always can &quot;kick down&quot; and call methods in </text><text styleclass="Class Name" translate="true">WSockLibrary</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> when necessary.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Next up, </text><text styleclass="Program Feature" translate="true">Sockets Connection</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> implements a number of classes that make it easy to set up a network link with a Socket at either end. At this basic level you can send and receive bytes and arrays of bytes across the link.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">A level further up you&apos;ll find that each Socket can provide you with a read stream and a write stream for easy streaming of data using the standard Smalltalk Stream protocol. This is a very powerful level of interface and one that you will probably find yourself using most often.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">At the highest level it is possible to connect a Dolphin STB filer onto either of the two Socket streams, thus allowing serializable objects to be easily passed back and forth across a connection.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">This text is intended to provide a general user&apos;s guide on how to use </text><text styleclass="Program Feature" translate="true">Sockets Connection</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">. We will not touch any further on the lowest level of interface; the </text><text styleclass="Class Name" translate="true">WSockLibrary</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> function calls. If you need more information on these then you should consult the Microsoft SDK documentation or a suitable book. We will run, however, through a number of scenarios for using the higher levels of interface. If you want reference information about each of the classes and the methods that they provide, then you should consult the code directly. All of the classes and methods are commented appropriately</text></para>
  </body>
</topic>
