<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../helpproject.xsl" ?>
<topic template="Default" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../helpproject.xsd">
  <title translate="true">Welcome to Dolphin Smalltalk 7</title>
  <body>
    <header>
      <para styleclass="Heading1"><text styleclass="Heading1" translate="true">Welcome to Dolphin Smalltalk 7</text></para>
    </header>
    <para styleclass="Heading2"><text styleclass="Heading2" style="font-style:normal;">Welcome</text><text styleclass="Heading2" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true"> to a New Dimension in Application Development</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal">Dolphin Smalltalk 7 is</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> an object-oriented development environment for Microsoft Windows</text><text styleclass="Normal" style="font-family:Symbol;" translate="true">Ô</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">. As you might expect from any set of programming tools, you can quickly use it to build and test professional Windows executables (EXEs) and COM components (DLLs). But here the similarity ends. Under the covers you will find it quite different from other programming environments you may be used to. The reason for this difference is: </text><text styleclass="Program Feature" translate="true">Smalltalk</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">.</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Smalltalk is not just a programming language. It is a completely object oriented development system that just happens to have an object oriented programming language (Smalltalk, the language) at the front end. When you double-click on the </text><text styleclass="Normal">Dolphin Smalltalk</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> icon you are opening a set of windows onto a world of objects. Everything you deal with inside </text><text styleclass="Normal">Dolphin</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true"> is an object. &#160;Numbers are objects. Text strings are objects. Even the development tools are objects. All of these objects in this world are constantly interacting, sending messages to one another and their behaviour is dictated by the Smalltalk code that lies behind them. </text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Heading2" style="font-style:normal;" translate="true">A World of Live Objects</text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">All of the Smalltalk source code for the system is supplied to you but not as &quot;dead&quot; sample files that have to be compiled up to see how they work. The Smalltalk code that you see in the Dolphin browsers is the exact code that you see running before your eyes. If you make a change to an object then its behaviour changes instantly with no need to re-link or restart the system. Imagine this, you can modify (or even create) your application objects while they are working, while they are interacting with one another. This is a truly dynamic, seamless approach to programming that makes it feel like your application objects are almost &quot;alive&quot;. </text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">Once you have experienced the Smalltalk way we doubt that you&apos;ll want to return to the static, file-based approach of other languages like Java and C#. </text></para>
    <para styleclass="Normal"><text styleclass="Normal" style="text-decoration:underline;" translate="true">At least, we hope so</text><text styleclass="Normal" translate="true">.</text></para>
  </body>
</topic>
